בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is בבא בתרא Bava Batra
פ"ד, pe dalet, 84. We pick up with the גמרא, Gemara, the
beginning of the גמרא Gemara after the משנה mishna on פ"ג עמוד
ב', pe gimmel amud bet, right after משנה mishna that talked after
dealing with the case of the different parts of an animal
about when you buy one thing part of thing you buy the
other, we got onto a new category of the idea of four
types of טעות, ta'ut, of mistake when you are purchasing something and
it turns out to be worse than the item that was agreed
upon or better than the item that was agreed upon, and the
basic principle of the משנה mishna was that if you say it's
going to be good wheat and it turns out to be bad,
then the person who was cheated was the purchaser and the buyer
and he has a right to demand
that his money back to nullify the sale but the seller cannot,
even if he has some reasons that he would want to. In
the reverse, if it was said bad and it turned out to
be good, then the buyer can say, "I misunderstood, I was tricked,
it was like whatever, מקח טעות, mekach ta'ut, not what I thought,"
and the buyer has the right to reverse it, and in a
case where it wasn't good or a difference of good or bad
but it was a different thing altogether, red wine versus white wine,
wine versus vinegar, doesn't matter really which is worth more or less,
people some people wanted one item and not the other, so that
was a two-sided mistake and either side can back out. So that's
the basic principles of the משנה. mishna. The משנה mishna does not
reference אונאה ona'ah at all, overcharging. A whole discussion of אונאה ona'ah
has to do with the question of how much was it, was
the item that was agreed upon, there was not a טעות, ta'ut,
but the fact that there was it was overcharged or undercharged could
be a reason to demand your money back or to nullify the
sale. It's like if you gross overcharging, I demand my money back.
But that's very different than the issues of our משנה mishna where
there was a degree of a mistake or about what the exact
item was. And it's going to be the גמרא's Gemara going to
make some type of a parallel but that doesn't even as we'll
see in a minute, but even that parallel does not mean that
it conceptually and הלכתית halachically is in the same category. For example,
what if the difference about good and bad wheat was less than
a sixth, right? Would the משנה mishna still apply? The הלכה halacha
about אונאה ona'ah is that you have time to ask for your
money back when you have a chance to show it
to relatives or a trade somebody who's in the business that can
tell you whether you were cheated or not. Is that the same
time frame here? What is the time frame here? So really it
seems to be a completely different category but nevertheless let's start and
see the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara at least makes an analogy
to the אונאה ona'ah discussion, although I would not say that it
is putting it in that category. So let's take a look. גמרא,
Gemara, two lines from the bottom of פ"ג עמוד ב'. pe gimmel
amud bet. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, מכר לו שווה חמש
בשש והוקר. Macher lo shaveh chamesh b'shesh vehukar.
Somebody now he is starting to tell a הלכה halacha not about
our משנה, mishna, about אונאה. ona'ah. Somebody sold something worth five and
he charged six for it. That's overcharging because it is one sixth
more. Now there's a whole discussion how do you figure the sixth,
by the original price of the object or by the or by
the money that was paid. And we're not going to worry about
that now, that's a whole discussion in בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, but
we're just going to work with the assumption that either one can
define a sixth. So in here it was overcharged, one dollar, let's
make it worth dollars or זוזים zuzim whatever, and one dollar is
a sixth of the final amount paid. So that's classic אונאה. ona'ah.
So therefore, it's אונאה ona'ah and the purchaser, the buyer who was
cheated, has the right to demand his money back or demand that
the sale be nullified. Not going to get into the different debates
about that, let's assume right now that it's either, either to keep
the sale and get his overcharged back or to negate the sale.
That was the initial scenario. So the purchaser has a right and
not the seller, because it was the purchaser who was cheated. But
now והוקר ועמד על שמונה. vehukar v'amad al shmoneh. Now the prices
have changed and that thing that originally was worth five is now
worth eight. So now the seller would ideally like to nullify the
sale and get the object back, because now he gave the buyer
something for six which is now worth eight. And the רשב"ם Rashbam
says that this change in price is during the period when the
seller has the right to demand his money back or to nullify
the sale, I mean his overcharged back or to nullify the sale,
which is the time it takes for him to show to his
relatives or to somebody in the business who would be able to
give him an assessment of whether he overpaid. All right, so does
the seller have the right in this case to demand his money
back? So because now he doesn't like the way it worked out.
מני דתניא, Manni detanya, so רב חסדא Rav Chisda says let's take
a look. So, מי נתאנה? Mi Nitaneh? So רב חסדא Rav Chisda
says let's take a look. Who is cheated? לוקח, Lokayach, it was
the buyer who was cheated. לוקח יכול לחזור בו ולא מוכר. Lokayach
yachol lachzor bo velo mocher. So, only the buyer has the right
to demand his overcharge back or to demand let's, you know, that
the sale be reversed, not the seller. The seller cannot. Why not?
משום דאמר ליה, Mishum d'amar leh, top of 84 עמוד א, amud
aleph, because the seller can say to the buyer, אילו לא עוניתן
לא הוית מצית הדר בך. Ilu lo onisan lo havist matzis hadar
bach. If you had not overcharged me, if you had not cheated
me, then we wouldn't be having this discussion, you obviously could not
reverse the sale. השתא דעוניתן מצית הדר בך? Hashta d'onisan matzis hadar
bach? Now that you overcharged me, you should now have the privilege
of being able to, you know, reverse the sale? That doesn't make
any sense. I'm the one that was hurt by this, that was
overcharged and cheated. That does not give you any privileges, so only
I can reverse it, you can't, even though now you have a
reason to reverse it. Now, that is so obvious that we might
ask what was the הוה אמינא hava amina otherwise. Well, the הוה
אמינא hava amina otherwise is that since the buyer can get his
money back until he has a chance to show, you know, to
his relatives, then conceptually I might say that the, it's not that
the sale was final and the buyer has a זכות חזרה, zchut
chazarah, a right to demand that it be nullified, but that the
sale is not final until he has a chance to show it
to his relatives. If you frame it that way, not that the
buyer, the person who was cheated has the right to demand that
it be nullified, but you frame it as the sale was not
final until, you know, you can check the price, then both sides
should have the right to reverse, so because the sale wasn't final.
So Rav Chisda says that is not the case. This is a
question of one side being wronged and that side having a right
to reverse it, and that does not give privileges to the other
side. Okay, and now Rav Chisda says, ותנא תונא, v'tana tuna, and
our ותנא תונא, tanna tuna, our תנא דידן, tanna didan, taught similarly.
תנא, Tanna, he taught similarly. יפות ונמצאו רעות לוקח יכול לחזור בו
ולא מוכר. Yafos v'nimtzu raos lokayach yachol lachzor bo velo mocher. If
it was good grain and then turned out to be bad, only
the buyer can reverse, you know, can nullify the sale and not
the seller. Now, if the point was that the going price did
not change, you know, that would be obvious, the seller wouldn't even
want to be reversing himself and you wouldn't even have to be
telling me that הלכה. halacha. So the only חידוש chidush is that
the seller now has a reason to reverse himself, that the prices
have changed and now the wheat is worth a lot more and
the seller would actually like to get it back even though it
was bad wheat. All right, and nevertheless the משנה mishnah says the
buyer can get it back and not the seller. ותנא תונא יפות
ונמצאו רעות לוקח יכול לחזור בו ולא מוכר. V'tana tuna yafos v'nimtzu
raos lokayach yachol lachzor bo velo mocher. So that shows that when
there is a right to nullify, it is a one-sided right, even
if the, and it does not stretch out the time in which
we say it takes for the sale to be final. Now again,
there are different issues. One is overcharging, one is the wrong, one
is, you know, or it's the wrong object, but it's the right
object but different as was described. But the גמרא Gemara is sort
of seeing them at least if not the same הלכה halacha in
the same conversation. We don't say the sale wasn't final,
we say that one side, the wronged side, has the right to
reverse it. All right, and now the גמרא Gemara says, ואמר רב
חסדא, v'amar Rav Chisda, now we're going to say the same thing
in reverse. Said Rav Chisda, מכר לו
שוה שש בחמש. machar lo shaveh shesh b'chamesh. Let's say it's the
reverse. Say something was worth six and sold for five, so that
was a case of אונאה, ona'ah, undercharging, where the seller was cheated.
And even though the seller is one seller, it happens sometimes, somebody
can realize, oh, there's a מציאה metziah here and the guy doesn't
know what he's selling. Okay, so the seller was cheated in this
exchange. And then, והוזלו ועמדו על ג'. v'huzlu v'amdu al gimmel. And
now, so the seller has a right to get his money back,
not the buyer, but now the stuff is that, you know, that
was good grain even though he bought it assuming it was bad,
you know, excuse me, the stuff that he paid, he underpaid for,
now it is worth like even less. The market collapsed. So even
his underpaying, he would like to reverse that, he actually wound up
paying now it's too much. That happened after the sale was, after
the sale was made, but before he had a chance to show
it to his friends and relatives. All right, so in this case,
מי נתאנה? mi nitaneh? Who was the one that was cheated? מוכר,
Mocher, the seller. The seller, you know, got less money than it
was worth. So מוכר יכול לחזור בו ולא לוקח. mocher yachol lachzor
bo velo lokayach. Only the seller has the right to reverse himself
even though now the buyer would like to reverse himself. Sorry, only
the seller. דאמר ליה, D'amar leh, because the seller can say to
him,
אילו לא נתאנה לא הוית מצית הדר בך, ilu lo nitan lo
havist matzis hadar bach, then there would be no question, the sale
was final at the moment of the exchange. and you would not
be able to reverse. השתא דצמצצת הדר פחת, Hashta detzimtzetzta hadar pachat,
now that you have wronged me and cheated me and paid me
less than it was worth, and that gives me a right to
demand a reversal, that why should that, your wronging me, give you
that right as well? Okay, same idea, makes a lot of sense.
ותנא תונא, Vetana tuna, and our תנא tanna taught similarly. Again, it's
just the mirror image of this. ותנא תונא, Vetana tuna, רעות ונמצאו
יפות, ra'os venimtze'u yafos, if they were bad grain and it was
discovered to be good, so the seller thought he was selling bad
and the buyer got a מציאה, metzia, got something better than was
promised. מוכר יכול לחזור בו ולא לוקח. Mocher yachol lachzor bo velo
loke'ach.
Only the seller can reverse himself, not the buyer, presumably even in
a case where the buyer would want to reverse himself. Okay, where
the market, you know, collapsed, collapsed. Nevertheless, only the seller can reverse
himself, not the buyer. Okay, all very straightforward and we certainly see
the parallel to the משנה. mishnah. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי
קמשמע לן מתניתין היא, mai kamashma lan masnisin hi, the גמרא Gemara
says, oh, that's all patently obvious, that's exactly the point of the
משנה, mishnah, that the wronged side has a right for reversal, to
reverse, and not the other side, even if presumably there was reason
now that the other side would like to reverse. You know, the
other side has an interest in reversing, tough luck, only the wronged
side has that right. That's clearly the point of the משנה. mishnah.
So what חידוש chiddush is רב חסדא Rav Chisda telling us? So
the גמרא Gemara now finally sort of points out the difference without
necessarily describing it in terms of that there's a הלכתית halakhic difference,
but at least the circumstantial difference
between overcharging and a mis- like a misrepresentation of the item. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this: No, אי מהמתניתין הוה אמינא דילמא
דרב חסדא שתיהי מצי הדר בהו. im masnisin hava amina dima derav
chisda shtayei matzi hadar beihu. If it was our משנה, mishnah, I
could have distinguished the cases. I could have said in a case
where it's exactly the item as was said, and it's just a
question of overcharging, maybe both sides could reverse. Why could both sides
reverse? For the reason, let's say, we said, that the sale isn't
final until you have a chance to show it to your friends
and relatives to check that you got a fair price. Now I
should say that that doesn't make total sense because then even if
it was sold at the right price, you should have a chance
to reverse it until you've had a chance to show it to
your friends and relatives. So maybe yes, or you could say that
in the case of overcharging, the הלכה halakha just is, if one
side was overcharged and cheated, under those circumstances maybe both sides can
ask for a reversal. That throws the whole sale into question because
clearly it was not the way that it should have been and
maybe that gives both sides the right to reverse. Okay, but how
about our case? Why would our case be only one side? If
when there was a- it was wrong, both sides have a right
to reverse, why not in our case? ומתניתין חסא לשמענא דלוקח לחזור
בו, Umasnisin hasa leshmena deloke'ach lachzor bo,
now there's a very question here about the exact גרסא, girsa, so
the simplest read of this and the תוספות Tosafos read is ומתניתין
הוה אמינא דמשום דכתיב רע רע יאמר לוקח, umasnisin hava amina demishum
dechsiv ra ra yomar loke'ach,
just sort of those there's like six or eight extra words. But
the משנה mishnah is different because the משנה, mishnah, I would say,
it's only one-sided. Why? Because the buyer is always sort of, you
know, when you haggle, the buyer is always saying, ach, this is
really bad quality, right? And the seller's always saying, oh, let me
show you, I have the best wheat ever, this is the most
amazing wheat. So the buyer is- seller's always overclaiming the quality and
the buyer is always underclaiming. And since that's true, when it is
let's say, you know, claimed to be good and it winds up
being bad wheat, so in that case, you know, the buyer can
say, look, I was- bad sale, מקח טעות, mekach ta'us, it was
a mistake, you said it was good, it wound up being bad,
this was not what I expected. Okay, but if the seller wants
to say, look, it was not as we agreed because you know,
because we said it was good and it wound up being bad
and since it wasn't as we agreed, even I the seller should
have a right to reverse it. The buyer can say, no, even
when you said good, I know I- I knew you weren't- you
didn't mean good, you're always claiming it's better than it really is.
So it's not objectively that something wrong happened. All right? In the
case of overcharging or undercharging, objectively it was paid too much based
on its going price, going rate, or too little. And maybe when
too much or too little has been paid, that gives both sides
the right to demand a- to demand a reversal. But in this
case, a claim could be made that even though it was said
that it was good, I the buyer don't- never really believed you
anyway. So it's not clearly objectively different than was promised, because it
could be that the buyer- the seller was overclaiming and it was
understood that he was overclaiming and that there was not. Similarly, when
it was said to be bad and turned out good, it's not
clear that it was different than as described because it's possible that
even when the buyer was saying I'm buying it bad and because
of that I'm only going to pay X amount, that the seller
could claim I, that was just the way you the buyer talk,
and or the buyer could, anyway, that
and objectively it wasn't different than it was because even when the
buyer is saying bad, maybe everybody understands that it could objectively be
good. All right, so that's the point. But we don't make that
distinction. In both cases we say the side that was cheated has
a right to back out and not the other side, or the
side that got different than what they expected and was hurt by
it—might not be cheated, might not be intentional—doesn't matter I should mention
if any of this is intentional or not, but the side that
was hurt has the right to back out. But again, the Gemara
is saying I might have had a הוה אמינא Hava Amina that
when objectively there was a problem with the sale, both sides have
a right, and in our Mishnah, it's questionable if there was objectively
a problem because of the overclaims of the seller and the underclaims
of the buyer. But in the end, the halakha is in both
cases only the injured party has the right to reverse it. All
right, let's keep on going. שחמתית ונמצאת לבנה. Shachamtis venimtzet levanah. If
it was, the grain was claimed to be red and it turned
out white, since it's a different type of a thing, both sides
can back out. So the description, there's only two types of red,
apparently, two types of grain, white and red. And the word used
for red here is שחמתית, Shachamtis, like the חמה, Chamah, like the
sun. So let's take a look what the Gemara says. אמר רב
פפא, Amar Rav Papa, מדקתני לבנה שמע מינה, Midkatni Levanah Shema Minah,
since it says that the contrast is white and presumably here we
know that the other color of grain is red, so you're using
red to say שחמתית, Shachamtis, so you're basically saying that the sun
is red. שמע מינה Shema Minah from this we hear האי שמשא
סומקתא היא, Hai Shimsha Sumakta Hi, the sun is red. Okay, that's
how we know that the sun is red. Okay,
תדע Teda and objectively, why don't you just look at it? Well,
because if you just look at it, it's different colors at different
times. דקאסמי צפרא ופניא Dekasmi Tzafra Ufanya because in the morning at
dawn and at dusk, the sky is red, and that shows you
that the sun, and that's consistent with this idea that the sun
is objectively red. Ah, so why during the day does it not
appear red, it appears yellow? Or I'm sorry, the Gemara says והאי
דלא קחזינא כולי יומא, Ve'hai Delo Kachazina Kulei Yoma, and the fact
that we don't see it red the whole day, נהורין הוא דלא
ברי, Nehorin Hu Delo Bari, it's because our eyesight isn't great. It's
so strong during the day that somehow we're only, we're not able
to see the red color. But at night and at dusk when
it's darker, or at dusk and at dawn when it's darker, it's
not so bright, then we can see its true color. It's sort
of like when there's a solar eclipse and you're not blinded by
the light of the sun, you can see a part of the
sun that you normally don't see. Okay, now obviously that is not
the real reason why it's red in the morning and the evening,
it has to do with the fact that the light has further
distance to travel because it's not like at the top of the
sky, curvature, anyway, the light has further distance to travel and the
blue wavelength is shorter and the red wavelength is longer, so the
red wavelength gets to us faster than the blue, and anyway it
appears more red. But the Gemara did not know about wavelengths. Okay.
מיתיבי Meitivei against this argument that the sun is red. מראהו עמוק
מן העור Mar'ehu Amok Min Ha'or it says by צרעת Tzaraat that
the appearance is deeper than the skin, כמראה חמה עמוקה מן הצל.
Ke'mareh Chamah Amukah Min Hatzel. So since, and צרעת Tzaraat is white,
and the Gemara says why is it deeper than the skin, just
like we know that the appearance of sunlight is deeper than shade.
Okay, don't ask me what this means. This is Rashi all through
parshat תזריע, Tazria, and I don't begin to understand this. There's a
whole long Ramban, anyway, fine. But that's the claim
that sunlight and shade next to one another, the sunlight looks darker,
and that's what the pasuk means. So the Gemara says והתם לבן
הוא, Ve'hatam Lavan Hu, so and we know that צרעת Tzaraat is
white, and it's comparing it to the sun, so you see the
sun is white. No, the Gemara says כמראה חמה ולא כמראה חמה.
Ke'mareh Chamah Velo Ke'mareh Chamah. It means like sunlight but not like
the appearance of the sun exactly. כמראה חמה דעמוקה מן הצל, Ke'mareh
Chamah De'amukah Min Hatzel, analogous to the way sunlight is deeper, appears
deeper than shade, similar the צרעת Tzaraat on the skin appears deeper
than the skin. ולא כמראה חמה, Velo Ke'mareh Chamah, it's not exactly
like the appearance of the
sun, דאילו התם לבן והכא אדום De'ilu Hatam Lavan Vehacha Adom because
by צרעת Tzaraat we're dealing with
white and here it's red. So now the Gemara says ולמאי דסליק
דעתך מעיקרא, U'lemai Desalik Da'atach Me'ikara, that which we originally
thought, or that we were trying to argue that the sun is
really white light, if that's really true, הא קסמקי צפרא ופניא, Ha
Kasmki Tzafra Ufanya, so what theory did we have to explain why
it was red? Right, we see both phenomenon: a red sky in
dawn and dusk, and yellow sun, whatever, or you know, just say
white light in the middle of the day. So how if we
said that the real objective color was white, how do we explain
the redness at dawn and dusk?
בצפרא דחלפא אבורדי דגנידן Be'tzapra de'chalfa a'varda de'Gan Eden because in the
morning it is rising in the East and גן עדן Gan Eden
is the East, גן בעדן מקדם, Gan be'Eden mi'kedem, so it is
like reflecting the rose garden in גן עדן. Gan Eden. You didn't
know that there was a rose garden in גן עדן? Gan Eden?
You never promised me a rose garden. Well, if you do מצוות
mitzvot and get עולם הבא, Olam Ha'ba, you'll get the rose garden
of גן עדן, Gan Eden, so that gives it a red color.
And ובפניא דחלפא אפתחא דגיהנם, u've'panya de'chalfa a'pitcha de'Gehinnom, in the night,
apparently גיהנם Gehinnom is in the West and it's passing by גיהנם
Gehinnom and the fires and the red fires of גיהנם, Gehinnom, you
know, is what is what makes the sun appear red. ואיכא דאמרי
איפכא, Ve'ika de'amri ipcha, some say the opposite, so not that the
way the רשבא Rashba explains, still גן עדן Gan Eden is in
the East and גיהנם Gehinnom is in the West, but that the
color has to do with reflecting what is opposite the sun, not
what is alongside the sun. Okay, moving on. יין ונמצא חומץ שניהם
יכולים לחזור בהן. Yayin ve'nimtza chometz shneihem yecholim lachzor ba'hen. Wine and
vinegar, it was promised wine and found vinegar or vice versa, doesn't
matter which cost more or less, that was a different object that
was promised and both sides have the right to reverse themselves. Says
the גמרא, Gemara, לימא מתניתין רבי היא ולא רבנן. Leima matnitin Rabbi
hi ve'lo Rabbanan. Let's say our משנה Mishnah is רבי Rabbi and
not the רבנן Rabbanan of the following debate. דתניא, De'tanya, we taught
in the ברייתא, Baraita,
top of פד עמוד ב. Pei Daled Amud Bet.
יין וחומץ מין אחד הוא, רבי אומר שני מינים. Yayin ve'chometz min
echad hu, Rabbi omer shnei minim. Wine and vinegar is one type
of thing, one type of species, you know, and רבי Rabbi says
two. Now, what's that about? That's about the הלכה Halacha of תרומה.
Terumah. If I take, you know, from apples, take תרומה Terumah from
apples on pears, it doesn't work. If I take from good apples
on bad apples or bad apples on good apples, it does work.
What if I take from, I don't know, green apples on red
apples? Is that like apples and pears or is that apples and
apples? Right, comparing apples and apples. So that's a הלכה Halacha of
תרומה. Terumah. You have to decide if it's the same category if
you can take from one on the other. So the רבנן Rabbanan
say that it's all one category, you know, because it's just wine
that has turned. I mean, we're talking about wine and vinegar.
And רבי Rabbi says no, no, no, they are considered two categories
and you can't be מפריש תרומה mafrish Terumah from one to the
other.
So it seems like our משנה Mishnah is רבי Rabbi because our
משנה Mishnah gives a right to both sides to reverse when it's
a different type of a thing, not when it's just better or
worse. Better or worse wheat, you know, only the wrong side can
reverse. So here the fact that both sides can reverse shows that
it's two different types of things. So that does that specifically רבי's
Rabbi's position? So the גמרא Gemara says אפילו תימא רבנן. Afilu teima
Rabbanan. No, our משנה Mishnah could even be going like the רבנן
Rabbanan in תרומה. Terumah. עד כאן לא פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי. Ad
kan lo peligi Rabbanan alei de'Rabbi. The רבנן Rabbanan only argue on
רבי Rabbi אלא לעניין מעשר ותרומה ela l'inyan ma'aser ve'terumah when it
comes to תרומה ומעשר Terumah u'Ma'aser and you have to decide is
it the same type of object on the other, וכדרבי אילעא, u'che'Rabbi
Ilai, like רבי אילעא Rabbi Ilai teaches. דאמר רבי אילעא, De'amar Rabbi
Ilai, מניין לתורם מן הרע על היפה שתרומתו תרומה. minayin la'torem min
ha'ra al ha'yafeh she'trumato trumah. How do we know when somebody takes
from bad wheat grain on good grain, it still is חל, chal,
you've violated something but the תרומה Terumah works. How do you know
that? שנאמר, She'ne'emar, the פסוק Pasuk says ולא תשאו עליו חטא בהרימכם
את חלבו ממנו. ve'lo tisu alav cheit be'harimchem et chelbo mimenu. You
will not bear sin when you take the חלב, chelev, the best,
the choice from the תרומה. Terumah. So if you take something that's
not the choice and certainly if you take something that's inferior for
your תרומה, Terumah, you will be deserving of sin. So says רבי
אילעא, Rabbi Ilai, אם אינו קדוש נשיאות חטא למה. im eino kadosh
nesi'ut cheit lama.
So if when you took from bad on good it didn't actually
work, it was like, you know, taking bad on good it wouldn't
be חל, chal, it wouldn't be considered תרומה, Terumah, if it was
only תרומה Terumah if it was equal or better, then it wouldn't
say that you have to bear the sin if you take from
bad on good because you wouldn't accomplish anything. So there's no sin
to bear. מכאן, Mikan, so from here you understand לתורם מן הרע
על היפה שתרומתו תרומה. la'torem min ha'ra al ha'yafeh she'trumato trumah. That
when you take from bad on good you have violated something and
that's your sin, but the תרומה Terumah is still חל. chal. Okay
now that doesn't really explain it because it has to be bad
on good of the same מין, min, bad apples on good apples,
right, one bad apple ruining the bunch. But like that doesn't tell
you you can take from apples to pears. But what the גמרא
Gemara is saying is that since by תרומה Terumah we already have
this idea, you know, that like it doesn't have to be exactly
the same, that allows for a category, that allows us to consider
wine and vinegar in the same category. Not exactly clear how this
רבי אילעא Rabbi Ilai fits that idea personally, you know, sure bad
and good but still you have to define categories. It's clearer why
the גמרא Gemara understands the logic that operates in terms of the
case of transaction. Let's see how it contrasts it. אבל לעניין מקח
וממכר, Aval l'inyan mekach u'memkar, but when it comes to to transactions
דכולי עלמא איכא דניחא ליה בחמרא ולא ניחא ליה בחלא ואיכא דניחא
ליה בחלא ולא ניחא ליה בחמרא dechulei alma ika denichlei bechamra velo
nichlei bechala veika denichlei bechala velo nichlei bechamra that everybody agrees that
there's some people who prefer vinegar and some people who prefer wine,
maybe not all the time, but like sometimes you go to the
store and you only want to buy vinegar, and sometimes you go
and you only want to buy wine. So that's easier to understand
what the גמרא Gemara is saying. The גמרא Gemara saying is you
don't have to objectively define things as two separate species, right, two
separate categories, you know, you could define them as just, you know,
different types of wine. So red wine and white wine, right, red
wine and white wine, people are going to say those are, you
know, I mean now maybe they would, one has a name, you
know, they have different names, Bordeaux, Merlot, this, that, the other thing,
but you could say objectively for תרומה terumah purposes, red wine, white
wine, whatever, it's all wine, okay? But people still prefer sometimes one
over the other and asking for one and getting the other is
not better or worse, it's the different thing than I asked for.
Red peppers versus green peppers, it's not better or worse, you know,
it is I wanted one and not the other. So when it
comes to our משנה, Mishnah, says the גמרא, Gemara, objectively they can
be one type of thing, but still as long as within that
one type of thing sometimes when you want one, what's the word
like, not variation, but anyway, you know, but whatever, you know, one,
you know, one version, variation of that, right, you specifically want that
one and not the other one, and that is enough to say
that in a case of a transaction, you know, it was both
sides, it was different than what was asked for because people want
one and not the other, and therefore both sides can reverse themselves.
Okay, that was very nice. Let's take a look at the next
משנה. Mishnah. המוכר פירות לחברו. Hamocher peros lachaveiro.
Now we're getting to, it's very nice, we're actually touching on more
broader principles than just, you know, does the head come with the
feet. And now we're going to get to the principles of when
is a transaction final. So המוכר פירות לחברו, Hamocher peros lachaveiro,
if you're selling fruit, now fruit here could mean grain, okay, produce,
to your friend. משך ולא מדד קנה. Mashach velo madad kana. If
the buyer does a משיכה, meshichah, like draws the grain, you know,
to him,
and even if he did not measure it, the sale is final.
Now the רשב"ם Rashbam points out in all these cases the price
is agreed upon, you know, ten dollars a pound, because otherwise if
the price isn't agreed upon then a person could always say, "Oh
my God, you're charging me twenty dollars a pound, I never would
have bought it for that." So even though you don't know how
many pounds it is, you said ten dollars a pound, you took
the bag, you did משיכה, meshichah, the rest is just figuring out,
okay, how much I owe you. So even without measuring it, if
you did משיכה meshichah the sale is final. מדד ולא משך לא
קנה. Madad velo mashach lo kana. But if you measured it, okay
we got three pounds here, but you have yet to do an
act of קניין, kinyan, משיכה, meshichah, הגבהה, hagbah, whatever, then the sale
is not final and therefore you can, you know, both sides can
reverse because it's not the sale hasn't been made yet. אם היה
פיקח שוכר את מקומן. Im hayah pikeach socher es mekomon. If the
buyer was smart, you know, smart and I guess wanted the sale
to be final, you know, sometimes you want to wait till you've
made up your mind, but anyway, then you can just rent the
place so presumably we're talking it's in the store of the seller.
I mean we'll get, we'll see in the גמרא Gemara what the
location is. And then you could just say,
"Okay, before I have to שלעפ schlep these twenty bag pounds of
seed, you know, twenty pound bags of seed, you know, before I
own it, I'll just say here let me give you one dollar
and let me get rent the space that they're on for one
minute." And once I do that, now these twenty pound bags of
seed are on my property because I rented it for this minute
and now I'm קונה koneh it. Okay, הלוקח פשתן מחברו, Halokeach pishtan
mechaveiro,
if you are buying flax which is lighter, we're not talking about
twenty pound bags, in that case הרי זה לא קנה עד שיטלטלנו
ממקום למקום. harei zeh lo kana ad sheitaltelnu mimakom lemakom. You don't
get it by just doing משיכה, meshichah, dragging it out of its
place. You have to actually lift it up. And the way the
רשב"ם Rashbam explains it, I don't know if it's so clear from
the משנה, Mishnah, is that means you have to do הגבהה. hagbahah.
Since this is lighter and you can do הגבהה, hagbahah, it's not
final until you do הגבהה. hagbahah. אם היה מחובר לקרקע ותלש כל
שהוא קנה. Im hayah mechubar lakarka vesalash kol shehu kana. If you
were buying something that was attached to the ground, you know, like
I'll buy that apple off the tree from you and the guy
said yes, as soon as you plucked it off the tree that
also constitutes a מעשה קניין. ma'aseh kinyan. It's interesting what קניין kinyan
category that falls into. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. אמר
רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan. מדד
והניח על גבי סימטא קנה. Madad vehiniach al gabei simta kana. If
the seller measured it out and put it in front of you
basically on, you know, in a סימטא. simta. A סימטא simta is
like an alleyway and it's basically a place in which people can
have
like buyers and sellers do transactions there and when you're there it's
considered like a, like you have like it's not like... public thoroughfare
where the masses are always going through, it's like this place where
people can go
and they can have like temporary usage of it. So in that
type of a situation,
that's where we say משיכה meshikha works. משיכה meshikha doesn't work in
the seller's domain 'cause you haven't expressed your ownership by dragging it
while it's in the guy's store. You don't need משיכה meshikha when
it's in your domain. משיכה meshikha doesn't work in רשות הרבים reshus
harabim since it's a public thoroughfare, your dragging it does not really
show any sense of like stable ownership. But if you're in this
סמטא, simta, this alleyway, and you're dragging it, in that type of
a case, since you have like temporary right to use this place
that both you, the buyer, and the seller have
like the right to sort of use this, but it's not a
public space, that dragging shows an expression
of ownership. Okay, so that's the סמטא, simta, and that's where משיכה
meshikha works. So comes along רב אסי, Rav Assi, and he says
in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that even if you
didn't do משיכה, meshikha, even if you just—the seller just measured it
out and placed it in front of the buyer in the סמטא,
simta, the sale is final. Why? Not exactly clear. I mean, what
was the קניין? kinyan? But it seems like the logic is, since
the reason משיכה meshikha works here is because it's considered to be
like available for use for the buyer and the seller, and that
when the buyer does משיכה, meshikha, he's sort of exerting his domain
and his control over it, so maybe even
when the seller measures it out and puts it in front of
him, that idea of like placing it in front of the buyer
with the intent that the buyer owns it and is like, okay,
now the buyer is saying I'm now using this
סמטא simta to hold my grain, to be the place for my
grain. So that's okay, that's a pretty bold statement because there's none
of the classic קניינים. kinyanim. So it's going to be challenged. אמר
ליה רב זירא לרב אסי, amar leh Rav Zeira leh Rav Assi,
so רב זירא Rav Zeira said to רב אסי, Rav Assi, שמא
לא שאמר רבי אלא במודד לתוך קופתו? shema lo shamar Rebbi ella
be-moded le-tokh kupato? Maybe you, רב אסי, Rav Assi, when you heard
this teaching of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, maybe he was only talking
about where the seller was measuring it into the bags of the
buyer? Because and then it would work, because even without משיכה, meshikha,
you have another קניין, kinyan, a קניין כלי. kinyan kli. Since it's
in—if I'm the buyer, it's in my bags, my bags is sort
of like my domain. And maybe if my bags are in your
store, I'm not exerting that sense of ownership, but again, in this
more semi-private space of the סמטא simta and it's in my bags,
in a thing I own, then it's like it's in my property.
So he says, I could understand that if he measured it into
the guy's bags, but I don't understand that if he just put
it on the ground. שמא לא שאמר רבי אלא במודד לתוך קופתו?
shema lo shamar Rebbi ella be-moded le-tokh kupato? אמר
ליה, amar leh, he said back to him, דמיא לי רבנן כלא
גמר אינש שמעתא.
damya lee rabbana ke-lo gamar
inish shem'ata. It seems to me like this rabbi, you, it's like
you never learned a דף גמרא. daf Gemara. Okay, what a stupid
point. If that were the case,
מדלתוך קופתו מימרא בעי? madu le-tokh kupato memra ba-i? So if we
were talking about
the seller pouring it into the bag of the buyer, then
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would not have made a point of teaching
this as some innovative teaching, right? There would not have been this
tradition that he had taught it, because that's the standard הלכה. halakhah.
The standard הלכה halakhah is that when the stuff is in the
כלי של לוקח, keli shel loke'ach, in the vessels of the buyer,
and it's in a סמטא, simta, that the buyer owns it. So
if רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was saying I have something a חידוש
chiddush to teach, just measuring it out in the סמטא simta is
enough, clearly he would have only have said that if he was
talking even without it being in the כלי של לוקח. keli shel
loke'ach. So of course I did not get it wrong. Of course
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was teaching a bigger חידוש chiddush than that.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. קיבלה מיניה או לא
קיבלה מיניה? kiblah minei oh lo kiblah minei?
So did רב זירא Rav Zeira accept this response? Did he buy
it that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was even making this teaching even
straight on the ground of the סמטא? simta? So תא שמע, ta
shema, come and hear, דאמר רבי ינאי אמר רבי, de-amar Rabbi Yannai
emar Rabbi, רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai said in the name of רבי,
Rebbi, חצר השותפים קונים זה מזה. khatzer ha-shutafim konim zeh mizeh. Now
I don't know why that teaches you about רב זירא, Rav Zeira,
but okay. Here's another teaching that might show that a סמטא simta
could work by itself, because it says if you are in a
domain owned by partners and they want to sell one to the
other, and again, a סמטא simta is sort of seen as something
that functions like that, then in that type of a case, the
two partners or the buyer and seller, they can purchase from one
another in that domain. So what the גמרא, Gemara, תוספות Tosafot explains
what the גמרא Gemara thinks this means is that קונים זה מזה
konim zeh mizeh means almost like the חצר khatzer is... קונים זה
מזה. konim ze mize. That if you do something to sort of
you can use that חצר chatzer to be like your private domain
and to be קונה koneh as a קנין חצר. kinyan chatzer. So
it says that seems to be consistent with Rav Assi saying in
the name of Rabbi Yochanan, if the seller puts it in front
of the buyer, the buyer is now going to use the domain
to function as his private domain in order to be קונה. koneh.
And you don't need משיכה meshicha and you don't need כלי. kli.
So that seems to be would be consistent. מאי
לאו אגבי קרקע mai lav agabi karka are we not talking even
when it's straight on the ground? לא לתוך קופתו, lo letoch kuppato,
no,
it just means קנינים kinyanim work there, but it still would be
as opposed to when I'm in the seller's store, it doesn't work
if it's in my bag, when it's in a חצר של שותפים,
chatzer shel shutfin, a space owned by both sides or in a
סמטא, simta, it does work when it's inside of my bag or
it does work when there's משיכה. meshicha. לא לתוך קופתו, lo letoch
kuppato, no, not on the ground, only with some other קנין kinyan
taking place. הכי נמי מסתברא hachi nami mistavra says the גמרא Gemara
that also makes sense, דאמר רב יעקב אמר רבי יוחנן d'amar Rav
Yaakov amar Rabbi Yochanan מדד והניח אגבי סמטא לא קנה. madad v'heniach
agabi simta lo kana. We have a statement from Rav Yaakov in
the name of Rabbi Yochanan that is the exact opposite of Rav
Assi's statement. Rav Yaakov quotes Rabbi Yochanan as saying if you measured
it out and put it down in a סמטא, simta, the seller,
and put it down in a סמטא simta in front of the
buyer, it doesn't work. Okay, these now of course maybe one of
them got confused between קנה kana and לא קנה. lo kana. But
but we have contradictory statements.
קשיין אהדדי, kashyan ahadadi, these are directly contradictory, exact same scenarios, seller
measuring it out, putting it down on the סמטא, simta, one version
of Rabbi Yochanan says he owns it, one version says he doesn't
own it. קשיין אהדדי. kashyan ahadadi. אלא לאו שמע מינה ela lav
shma mina כאן במודד לתוך קופתו כאן במודד על גבי קרקע. kan
b'moded letoch kuppato kan b'moded al gabi karka. שמע מינה. shma mina.
The only way to reconcile these teachings is that the teaching where
Rabbi Yochanan says it works is when it was being poured into
the purchaser's vessels, you know, into his sacks, and then it works
because of קנין כלי. kinyan kli. And the version that he says
it doesn't work is when it was just being placed directly on
the ground. So you see in the end even though Rav Assi
was very offended and he made like a disparaging remark to Rav
Zeira, the גמרא Gemara in the end sides with Rav Zeira, that
this קנין kinyan does not work on the ground, it only works
in the in the vessel of the purchaser and actually Rabbi Yochanan
himself taught both things and it depends and the difference is whether
it was into the vessel of the buyer or not. שמע מינה.
shma mina. Okay, so even though the גמרא Gemara sort of could
end here, it wants to further see if we can, you know,
even, you know, even from our משנה Mishnah itself demonstrate the rightness
of this conclusion. Let's take a look. תא שמע, ta shma, come
here. מדד ולא משך לא קנה. madad v'lo mashach lo kana. Our
משנה Mishnah says if you just measured it out and didn't do
משיכה, meshicha, it doesn't work. Okay, מאי לאו בסמטא? mai lav b'simta?
Are we not talking about a סמטא? simta? So you see that's
clear, just measuring it out doesn't work.
לא ברשות הרבים. lo b'reshus harabbim. No, no, no, we're talking that
it happened in the public thoroughfare. גמרא Gemara says no, that can't
be the case of the משנה Mishnah that this transaction is happening
in the רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. אי הכי אימא רישא. ei hachi
eima reisha. משך ולא מדד קנה. mashach v'lo madad kana.
The first case says that משיכה meshicha does work. משיכה ברשות הרבים
מי קניא? meshicha b'reshus harabbim mi kanya? That can't be talking about
the רשות הרבים reshus harabbim because משיכה meshicha doesn't work in רשות
הרבים. reshus harabbim. ואביי ורבא דאמרי תרוייהו va'Abaye v'Rava d'amri tarveihu Abaye
and Rava both say מסירה קונה ברשות הרבים mesira koneh b'reshus harabbim
handing over the reins, that can work in רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim.
But מסירה קונה ברשות הרבים mesira koneh b'reshus harabbim ובחצר שאינה של
שניהם u'vechatzer she'eina shel shneihem
in like a domain that neither of them have rights to or
and you know ומשיכה קונה בסמטא ובחצר ששניהם u'meshicha koneh b'simta u'vechatzer
she'shneihem
but משיכה meshicha only works in an alleyway where both of them
have rights but it's more like private rights, not a public thoroughfare,
or literally in a yard owned by both of them. ובחצר ששניהם.
u'vechatzer she'shneihem. והגבהה קונה בכל מקום v'hagbaha koneh b'chol makom and הגבהה
hagbaha works everywhere.
So since the משנה Mishnah says that you do משיכה, meshicha, we're
obviously talking about a סמטא simta because that's where משיכה meshicha works.
And the משנה Mishnah also says that measuring out by itself doesn't
work. So the simple read of the משנה Mishnah is we're talking
about משיכה meshicha and it's a straight proof like we concluded that
measuring out in a סמטא simta doesn't work, only משיכה meshicha does
or only כלי של קונה. kli shel koneh. So that's really no
question what the פשט pshat is. But the גמרא Gemara is now
going to try to have a very tortured explanation to make it
not say that. So let's take a look. ובחצר ששניהם משיכה קונה
בסמטא. u'vechatzer she'shneihem meshicha koneh b'simta.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, מאי משך נמי דקתני מרשות הרבים
לסמטא. mai mashach nami d'kasani mereshus harabbim l'simta. No, no, no, when
the משנה Mishnah says you're doing משיכה, meshicha, it means you're doing
משיכה meshicha from we are talking that the transaction is happening in
רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. The משנה Mishnah that says משיכה meshicha works
and that's why measuring out doesn't work. The משנה Mishnah that says
משיכה meshicha works means you do משיכה meshicha from the רשות הרבים
reshus harabbim and you bring it into a סמטא simta and therefore
it'll work because it's in a סמטא. simta. If you measure it
out it won't work because you're still in the רשות הרבים. reshus
harabbim. If you were to go to the סמטא. simta. measure it
out it would, but you're starting by being situated in the רשות
הרבים. reshut harabim. Okay, אי הכי ei hachi says the גמרא, Gemara,
אימא סיפא. eima seifa.
Let's look at the last case of the משנה. mishna. אם היה
פיקח שוכר מקומו, im haya pikeach socheir mekomo, if the buyer was
smart, he wouldn't have to do משיכה meshicha or anything, just rent
the space from the seller. So ואי ברשות הרבים מי מנגר, ve-ibe-reshut
harabim mi managar, if it's in an alleyway, there are people who
own the alleyway that you could talk about renting it, but in
a public thoroughfare, who's he renting it from? The fact that it
gives renting as an option makes it clear that we're not in
a public thoroughfare. So the גמרא Gemara says no, הכי קאמר, hachi
kamar, no no no, this is what the משנה mishna means. ואם
ברשות בעלים היא, ve-im bi-reshut bealim hi, and in a completely different
scenario, if the guy was selling it to you not in the
רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, אם היה פיקח שוכר מקומו, im haya pikeach
socheir mekomo, then you could always rent the space and be קונה
koneh that way. So the simple read of the משנה mishna is
that it's taking place in a סימטא. simta. It says משיכה meshicha
works, measuring it out does not work. Parenthesis, כליו של לוקח keilo
shel lokeach also works, and finally, if you wanted to, you can
rent the סימטא simta for your private use, you know, from the
people who own that alleyway, and then that will also work. That's
the simple read of the משנה. mishna. But in order that it's
to say that it's not definitive against the idea that measuring out
in a סימטא simta does not work, we can read it to
say if you're in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, drag it into the
סימטא, simta, that works. Measuring in the רשות הרבים reshut harabim itself
does not work, and in a different scenario, you can choose to
rent it and that would also work. Okay, we will pick up
with this tomorrow.